The issue is, there are many qualitative things that we just can't put our finger on. So, think about hearing your favorite song for the first time. What were you doing?
La cuestión es, hay muchas cosas cualitativas que simplemente no podemos entender. Piensen cuando escucharon su canción favorita por primera vez. ¿Qué estaban haciendo?
How did you feel? Did you get goosebumps? Or did you get fired up? Hard to describe, right? See, parts of us feel so simple, but under the surface, there's really a ton of complexity. And translating that complexity to machines is what makes them modern-day moonshots. And I'm not convinced that we can answer these deeper questions with just ones and zeros alone. So, in the lab, I've been creating art as a way to help me design better experiences for bleeding-edge technology. And it's been serving as a catalyst to beef up the more human ways that computers can relate to us. Through art, we're tacking some of the hardest questions, like what does it really mean to feel? Or how do we engage and know how to be present with each other? And how does intuition affect the way that we interact? So, take for example human emotion. Right now, computers can make sense of our most basic ones, like joy, sadness, anger, fear and disgust, by converting those characteristics to math. But what about the more complex emotions? You know, those emotions that we have a hard time describing to each other? Like nostalgia. So, to explore this, I created a piece of art, an experience, that asked people to share a memory, and I teamed up with some data scientists to figure out how to take an emotion that's so highly subjective and convert it into something mathematically precise. So, we created what we call a nostalgia score
¿Cómo se sintieron? ¿Sintieron escalofríos? ¿Estaban entusiasmados? Difícil de describir, ¿no? Partes de nosotros parecen muy simples, pero bajo la superficie hay toneladas de complejidad. Y trasladar esa complejidad a las máquinas es lo que hace a los modernos hitos históricos. Y no estoy convencido de que podamos responder estas preguntas complejas solo con unos y ceros. En el laboratorio, he creando arte como medio para ayudarme a diseñar mejores experiencias para el último grito en tecnología. Ha servido como catalizador para reforzar maneras humanas en que los ordenadores pueden relacionarse con nosotros. A través del arte, abordamos algunas preguntas difíciles, como, ¿qué significa realmente sentir? O cómo involucrarnos y conocer cómo estar presentes para el otro. O cómo la intuición afecta la manera en que interactuamos. Tomemos por ejemplo la emoción humana. Los ordenadores pueden sentir nuestras emociones más básicas, como alegría, tristeza, enfado, miedo y disgusto, convirtiendo estas características en matemáticas. ¿Y qué hay de las emociones más complejas? Saben, ¿esas emociones que nos cuesta describir al otro? Como la nostalgia. Para explorar esto, he creado una obra de arte, una experiencia, que pide a la gente compartir sus recuerdos y los uno a algunos datos científicos para descubrir cómo tomar emociones muy subjetivas y convertirlas en algo matemáticamente preciso. Creamos una puntuación de nostalgia
and it's the heart of this installation. To do that, the installation asks you to share a story, the computer then analyzes it for its simpler emotions, it checks for your tendency to use past-tense wording and also looks for words that we tend to associate with nostalgia, like "home," "childhood" and "the past." It then creates a nostalgia score to indicate how nostalgic your story is. And that score is the driving force behind these light-based sculptures that serve as physical embodiments of your contribution. And the higher the score, the rosier the hue. You know, like looking at the world through rose-colored glasses. So, when you see your score and the physical representation of it, sometimes you'd agree and sometimes you wouldn't. It's as if it really understood how that experience made you feel. But other times it gets tripped up and has you thinking it doesn't understand you at all. But the piece really serves to show that if we have a hard time explaining the emotions that we have to each other, how can we teach a computer to make sense of them? So, even the more objective parts about being human are hard to describe. Like, conversation. Have you ever really tried to break down the steps? So think about sitting with your friend at a coffee shop and just having small talk. How do you know when to take a turn? How do you know when to shift topics? And how do you even know what topics to discuss? See, most of us don't really think about it, because it's almost second nature. And when we get to know someone, we learn more about what makes them tick, and then we learn what topics we can discuss. But when it comes to teaching AI systems how to interact with people, we have to teach them step by step what to do. And right now, it feels clunky. If you've ever tried to talk with Alexa, Siri or Google Assistant, you can tell that it or they can still sound cold. And have you ever gotten annoyed when they didn't understand what you were saying and you had to rephrase what you wanted 20 times just to play a song? Alright, to the credit of the designers, realistic communication is really hard. And there's a whole branch of sociology, called conversation analysis, that tries to make blueprints for different types of conversation. Types like customer service or counseling, teaching and others. I've been collaborating with a conversation analyst at the lab to try to help our AI systems hold more human-sounding conversations. This way, when you have an interaction with a chatbot on your phone or a voice-based system in the car, it sounds a little more human and less cold and disjointed. So I created a piece of art that tries to highlight the robotic, clunky interaction to help us understand, as designers, why it doesn't sound human yet and, well, what we can do about it. The piece is called Bot to Bot and it puts one conversational system against another and then exposes it to the general public. And what ends up happening is that you get something that tries to mimic human conversation, but falls short. Sometimes it works and sometimes it gets into these, well, loops of misunderstanding. So even though the machine-to-machine conversation can make sense, grammatically and colloquially, it can still end up feeling cold and robotic. And despite checking all the boxes, the dialogue lacks soul and those one-off quirks that make each of us who we are. So while it might be grammatically correct and uses all the right hashtags and emojis, it can end up sounding mechanical and, well, a little creepy. And we call this the uncanny valley. You know, that creepiness factor of tech where it's close to human but just slightly off. And the piece will start being one way that we test for the humanness of a conversation and the parts that get lost in translation. So there are other things that get lost in translation, too, like human intuition. Right now, computers are gaining more autonomy. They can take care of things for us, like change the temperature of our houses based on our preferences and even help us drive on the freeway. But there are things that you and I do in person that are really difficult to translate to AI. So think about the last time that you saw an old classmate or coworker. Did you give them a hug or go in for a handshake? You probably didn't think twice because you've had so many built up experiences that had you do one or the other. And as an artist, I feel that access to one's intuition, your unconscious knowing, is what helps us create amazing things. Big ideas, from that abstract, nonlinear place in our consciousness that is the culmination of all of our experiences. And if we want computers to relate to us and help amplify our creative abilities, I feel that we'll need to start thinking about how to make computers be intuitive. So I wanted to explore how something like human intuition could be directly translated to artificial intelligence. And I created a piece that explores computer-based intuition in a physical space. The piece is called Wayfinding, and it's set up as a symbolic compass that has four kinetic sculptures. Each one represents a direction, north, east, south and west. And there are sensors set up on the top of each sculpture that capture how far away you are from them. And the data that gets collected ends up changing the way that sculptures move and the direction of the compass. The thing is, the piece doesn't work like the automatic door sensor that just opens when you walk in front of it. See, your contribution is only a part of its collection of lived experiences. And all of those experiences affect the way that it moves. So when you walk in front of it, it starts to use all of the data that it's captured throughout its exhibition history -- or its intuition -- to mechanically respond to you based on what it's learned from others. And what ends up happening is that as participants we start to learn the level of detail that we need in order to manage expectations from both humans and machines. We can almost see our intuition being played out on the computer, picturing all of that data being processed in our mind's eye. My hope is that this type of art will help us think differently about intuition and how to apply that to AI in the future. So these are just a few examples of how I'm using art to feed into my work as a designer and researcher of artificial intelligence. And I see it as a crucial way to move innovation forward. Because right now, there are a lot of extremes when it comes to AI. Popular movies show it as this destructive force while commercials are showing it as a savior to solve some of the world's most complex problems. But regardless of where you stand, it's hard to deny that we're living in a world that's becoming more and more digital by the second. Our lives revolve around our devices, smart appliances and more. And I don't think this will let up any time soon. So, I'm trying to embed more humanness from the start. And I have a hunch that bringing art into an AI research process is a way to do just that. Thank you. (Applause)
y es el corazón de esta instalación. Para conseguir esto, el sistema te pide compartir una historia, el ordenador la analiza por sus emociones más simples, y comprueba la tendencia a usar palabras en pasado y busca palabras que tendemos a asociar con la nostalgia, como "casa", "infancia" y "el pasado". Luego crea una puntuación de nostalgia que indica cuán nostálgica es su historia. Y la puntuación es la impulsora que hay detrás de estas esculturas de luz que sirven como encarnaciones físicas de su contribución. Cuanto más alta la puntuación, más rosa es el tono. Es como mirar el mundo a través de lentes rosas. Así, cuando uno ve su puntuación y su representación física, a veces estará de acuerdo, y a veces no lo estará. Es como si realmente entendiera cómo lo hizo sentir esa experiencia. Pero otras veces tropieza de tal modo que piensa que no le ha entendido en absoluto. Pero la obra sirve para mostrar que si se nos hace difícil explicar las emociones que tenemos a otro, ¿cómo enseñar a un ordenador a darles sentido? Incluso las partes más objetivas de los humanos son difíciles de describir. Como la conversación. ¿Alguna vez han intentado descomponer sus partes? Piensen en estar sentados con un amigo en una cafetería teniendo una conversación trivial. ¿Cómo saben cuándo dar un giro a la conversación? ¿Cómo saben cuándo cambiar de tema? ¿Y cómo saben, incluso, sobre qué tema discutir? La mayoría no piensa sobre esto, parece algo natural. Cuando conocemos a alguien, sabemos cómo manejar esto, y aprendemos qué temas discutir. Pero cuando se trata de enseñar a enseñar a la IA a interactuar con gente, tenemos que enseñarle paso por paso qué hacer. Y ahora mismo, parece difícil. Si incluso tratan de hablar con Alexa, Siri o el asistente de Google, pueden decir que él o ellos aún suenan fríos. Y, ¿alguna vez incluso se han enfadado cuando no han comprendido qué estaban diciendo y tienen que reformular 20 veces lo que dicen para reproducir una canción? Para dar crédito a los diseñadores, la comunicación realista es muy difícil. Y hay una rama completa de la sociología, llamada análisis de la conversación, que intenta hacer planos de los diferentes tipos de conversación. Tipos como servicio al cliente, consejeros, enseñanza y otros. He estado colaborando con un analista de la conversación en el laboratorio para tratar de ayudar a los sistemas de IA a mantener conversaciones más humanas. Cuando tienes una interacción con un chatbox en tu teléfono o sistemas basados en voz en tu coche, suena un poco más humano y menos frío e inconexo. He creado una obra de arte que trata de iluminar la robótica, la interacción difícil para ayudarnos a entender, como diseñadores, por qué no suena humano aún, y qué podemos hacer. Esta obra se llama Bot to Bot y pone un sistema a conversar con otro y lo expone al público general. Y uno acaba teniendo algo que intenta imitar la conversación humana, pero se queda corto. A veces funciona y a veces se queda en estos, bueno, ciclos de malentendidos. Aunque una conversación máquina a máquina pueda tener sentido, gramatical y coloquialmente, aún sigue pareciendo algo frío y robótico. Y, a pesar de cumplir todos los puntos, el diálogo carece de alma y esa peculiaridad única hace de cada uno lo que es. Puede que si bien podía ser gramaticalmente correcto y usa todos los hashtags y emojis correctos, acaba sonando mecánico, y bueno, un poco siniestro. Y lo llamamos valle misterioso. El factor siniestro de la tecnología donde es cercana a lo humano pero está fuera de lugar. Y la pieza acabará siendo una forma de probar la humanidad en una conversación y las piezas perdidas en la traducción. Hay otras cosas perdidas en la traducción, también, como la intuición humana. Ahora, los ordenadores están ganando más autonomía. Pueden hacer cosas por nosotros, como cambiar la temperatura de casa según nuestras preferencias e incluso nos ayudan a conducir por la autopista. Pero hay cosas que Uds. y yo hacemos en persona que son difíciles de traducir a IA. Piensen en la última vez que vieron a un antiguo compañero de clase o colega. ¿Los abrazo o les dio la mano? Probablemente no lo pensó porque han tenido tantas experiencias acumuladas que les hizo hacer uno u otro. Y como artista, siento el acceso a la propia intuición, el conocimiento inconsciente, que nos ayuda a crear cosas maravillosas. Grandes ideas, de lo abstracto, en un lugar de nuestra consciencia que es la culminación de todas nuestras experiencias. Si queremos que se relacionen con nosotros y ayudan a amplificar habilidades creativas, necesitamos empezar a pensar cómo hacer que sean intuitivos. Quiero explorar cómo algo como la intuición humana puede ser directamente traducida a la inteligencia artificial. Y creé una obra que explora ordenadores basados en intuición en un espacio físico. Esta obra se llama Wayfinding, está configurada como una brújula simbólica que tiene cuatro esculturas quinéticas. Cada una representa una dirección, norte, este, sur y oeste. Y hay sensores configurados encima de cada escultura que capturan cuán lejos estás de ellas. Y los datos que coleccionan acaban cambiando la forma en que la escultura se mueve y la dirección de la brújula. La cosa es, la pieza no funciona como una puerta automática que solo se abre cuando uno pasa frente a ella. La contribución es solo una parte de nuestras experiencias vividas. Y esas experiencias afectan la manera en que se mueve. Cuando uno camina frente a ella, empieza a usar todos los datos que capturó a lo largo de su historial de exposición, o es intuición, para responder mecánicamente basado en lo que aprendió de otros. Y lo que acaba pasando es que como participantes empezamos a aprender el nivel de detalles que necesitamos para manejar las expectativas tanto de humanos como de máquinas. Casi podemos ver nuestra intuición interpretada en el ordenador, imaginando todos los datos siendo procesados por el ojo de la mente. Mi esperanza es que este tipo de arte nos ayudará a pensar diferente sobre nuestra intuición y cómo aplicarla a la IA en el futuro. Son unos cuantos efectos sobre cómo uso el arte para avivar mi trabajo como diseñador e investigador de inteligencia artificial. Y lo veo como una forma crucial para avanzar en innovación. Hay un montón de extremos cuando nos referimos a la IA. Películas famosas la muestran como esta fuerza destructiva mientras la publicidad la muestra como una salvadora para resolver alguno de los problemas más complejos del mundo. Pero independientemente de donde te encuentres es difícil negar que vivimos en un mundo que se vuelve más digital a cada segundo. Nuestras vidas giran en torno a nuestros dispositivos y demás Y no creo que esto desaparezca pronto. Intento incrustar más humanidad desde el principio. Tengo la corazonada de que llevar el arte al proceso de investigación IA es una manera de hacer esto. Gracias. (Aplausos)